Guide to the Bard Family Papers
Bard College Archives
Bard Family Papers
1638 - 1899
This collection documents the life and activities of members of the Bard family over the course of five generations, beginning with Peter Bard (1679-1734), and ending with John Bard (1818-1899), who founded Bard College with his wife, Margaret Johnston Bard (1825-1875). Peter Bard came to the United States in 1706 and settled in Delaware. It was here that he met Dinah Marmion, who he married in 1709 and with whom he had eight children. The eldest son, John (1716-1799), married Susanne Valleau in 1737, and together they moved to Hyde Park, New York. John became a physician and together they had six children, the most notable of whom was Dr. Samuel Bard. Samuel attended King’s college (later Columbia); was imprisoned in France during the Seven Years War; received medical training in Edinburgh; launched and served as the first president of the College of Physicians and Surgeons in New York; and served as a professor and a Trustee of Columbia College. Samuel was a leader in American medical education. He wrote multiple medical books, and, though a Loyalist during the Revolution, served as George Washington’s personal physician. Samuel was not only a successful physician, he also accumulated large amounts of land in the Hyde Park, New York area, renting out parcels of land to tenants. He married his cousin, Mary Bard in 1770, and together they had eight children, three of whom survived to adulthood: Eliza Bard McVickar (1789-1838); William Bard (1778-1853); and Susannah Bard Johnston (1772-1845). Susannah was the eldest daughter of Samuel and Mary. In 1792, she married John Johnstone. Together, Susannah and John had twelve children. Their eldest son, Francis Upton Johnston (1796-1858) studied under his grandfather, Dr. Samuel Bard, attending the College of Physicians and Surgeons, and later was the attending physician at the New York Hospital. This collection contains correspondence documenting family matters, illness, local news, thoughts on religion and books, and academic and professional concerns. Materials also document the business and professional affairs of the family, including deeds of land, leases and indentures, three manuscript volumes containing the text of lectures on natural philosophy delivered by Samuel Bard to students at Columbia College. Also included are several portraits of family members, multiple wills, two framed copies of a genealogical chart, documents about the founding of St. Stephen's College in 1860, and a bound manuscript of family recipes titled "Receipt Book."
5.5 Linear Feet, 7 Boxes; Also includes 4 portraits and 2 genealogy charts
Bard Family; Sands, Arthur
Bard College Archives Stevenson Library 1 Library Road Annandale-on-Hudson, NY 12504
Bard, Samuel, 1742-1821; Bard, William,--1778-1853; Bard, John, 1819-1899; Bard, John, 1716-1799; Columbia College (New York, N.Y.).--College of Physicians and Surgeons.--Faculty; College teachers; Johnston, Francis U.--1796-1858; Hospitals--New York (State)--New York; Medical colleges--New York (State)--New York; Medicine--Study and teaching; Medical students--New York (State)--New York; Medicine--Practice--New York (State)--New York; Physicians; Real estate investment; Real property--Upstate New York (N.Y.); St. Stephen's College (Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y.); King's College New York, N.Y.; Genealogy
Some items are stored separately, these items include: Bound Lecture Books, Bound Prayer Book, several 18th and early 19th c. framed portraits and two framed genealogical charts.
Bard Family Papers at Columbia University. Miscellanies (3 scrapbooks containing clippings, manuscript letters, engravings pertaining to the founding and administration of St. Stephen’s College in the 19th c.) at Bard College. The Sands Family Papers at Bard College.
Some materials have been glued down onto cardstock paper
Conservation Notes
This collection is separated into four series: 1) Personal Materials 2) Real Property and Legal Documents 3) Images of the Family 4) Bound Manuscripts
None
Materials were donated by Arthur Sands, grandson of William Bard, in 1938-1939 to the Bard College Library. Three bound manuscripts of lectures delivered at Columbia University were donated by John Bard to St. Stephen’s College in the 19th Century. Portrait of John Johnston was donated by [add name here] in ca. 2015.
Peter Bard was the first member of the Bard family in the United States. A Huguenot, Peter Bard was born in France in 1679, and was eventually forced to flee with his father due to religious persecution under Louis XIV. Arriving in the United States in 1706, he settled down in New Jersey, near Philadelphia, where he bought a large tract of land in the Burlington township in 1714. It was here that he met Dinah Marmion, who he married in 1709. Peter Bard would continue on to serve on the Colonial Council for New Jersey, become a Commanding Colonel of a foot regiment in 1722, and became a judge for the supreme court of New Jersey. Together, Peter and Dinah had eight children.
The eldest son of Dinah and Peter, John, was born in 1716. John married Susanne Valleau in 1737, and together they moved to Hyde Park, New York. John became a physician, and even served as a family physician to George Washington when he was a General. As a physician, John recommended the purchase of Bedloe's Island (now the Statue of Liberty), as a quarantine site for the isolation of contagious diseases. He also served as the first President of the New York Medical Society. John and Susanne had six children. Their daughter Susanna married Nathaniel Pendelton, who was Alexander Hamilton’s second in the famous duel with Aaron Burr in 1804. Of their children, the most notable was Dr. Samuel Bard.
Samuel was born in Philadelphia in 1742. A sickly child, he had to be removed from school when he was 14 years old. However, this did not stop him from pursuing higher education and he went on to attend King’s College. In 1761, Samuel left to go to England and spent time in London before moving on to study medicine in Edinburgh; but on the second of November, his ship was captured by the French, being thought to be British during the seven years war. Samuel was imprisoned in Bayonne Castle in the small town of St. Jean De Luz, France. Samuel quickly wrote to Benjamin Franklin, who then intervened on his behalf and Samuel was released from the French prison in April of 1762. Later that year, Samuel began college in Edinburgh, studying natural philosophy, anatomy, and chemistry. After graduating as a physician, Samuel returned to New York. In New York, Samuel launched and served as the first president of the College of Physicians and Surgeons, the first medical school in New York City. This medical school was attached to King’s College, later Columbia College. The College pf {physicians and Surgeons was the first medical school to grant the Doctor of Medicine degree in American. Here, he also served as a professor of the theory and practice of medicine, chemistry, natural philosophy, and astronomy. He also served as a Trustee of Columbia College from 1787 to 1804. Along with the college, Samuel founded New York Hospital in 1771.Samuel was not only a leader in American medical education, he also wrote multiple medical books, including one on Midwifery. He also served as George Washington’s personal physician. Samuel was not just a successful physician, he also accumulated large amounts of land in the Hyde Park, New York area, renting large amounts of the land out to tenants and experimenting with sheep farming. He married his cousin, Mary Bard in 1770, and had five children together.
Susannah Bard was the eldest daughter of Samuel and Mary, born in 1772. In 1792, she married John Johnstone. John Johnstone was Judge of the Court of Common Pleas of Dutchess County. Together, Susannah and John had twelve children. Susannah was a caring mother and a devoted Christian, often worrying about her children and protecting their souls through the church. Susannah and John often had money problems, and could only afford to send one child to college. They chose their eldest son, Francis Upton Johnston, born in 1796. Francis Upton studied under his grandfather, Samuel Bard, attending the College of Physicians and Surgeons. He graduated college in 1820, and by 1828, he was the attending physician at the New York Hospital. In 1822, he married Mary Williamson, and together they had nine children.
William Bard, the youngest son of Samuel and Mary Bard was born in 1778. He attended Columbia college and graduated in 1798, later becoming a member of the Society of the Cincinnati. In 1802, he married Catharine Cruger and together they had fourteen children. Their son, John, born in 1819, was also a member of the Society of the Cincinnati. John married Maragaret Taylor Johnston in 1849, and together they had 4 children. John founded St. Stephen’s College in 1860, which would become Bard College in 1935. Margaret died in 1875, and John remarried in 1876 to Annie Belcher, with whom he had one child.
1704 Edward Hyde Lord Cornbury grants land in Hyde Park to Peter Fauconnier
1706 Peter Bard (1679-1734) arrives in the United States
1714 Peter Bard (1679-1734) purchases a large tract of land in the Burlington Township, NJ
1716 John Bard (1716-1799) is born to Peter (1679-1734) and Dinah Bard (1693-1760)
1722 Peter Bard (1679-1734) is made Colonel of a New Jersey Foot Regiment
1737 John Bard (1716-1799) marries Susanne Valleau (1721-1784); couple move to Hyde Park, NY
1742 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) is born
1756 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) is pulled out of school due to illness
1759 Samuel Bard (1742-1824) graduates from King's College
November, 1761 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) is captured by the French and imprisoned
1762 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) is released from French imprisonment on the behest of Benjamin Franklin
September, 1762 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) begins medical training in Edinburg
1765 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) receives his M.D.
1767 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) establishes the College of Physicians and Surgeons
1769 The first medical degrees are conferred at the College of Physicians and Surgeons
1770 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) marries his cousin, Mary Bard (1746-1821)
1771 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) founds New York Hospital
1772 Susannah Bard (1772- ) is born to Samuel Bard (1742-1821) and Mary Bard (1746-1821)
1775 The Revolutionary War begins
1775 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) leaves New York City with his family to stay in Hyde Park, New York
1776 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) returns to New York City, while possessed by the enemySamuel Bard (1742-1821) returns to New York City, while possessed by the enemy
1776 Instruction at the College of Physicians and Surgeons is suspended due to war
1778 William Bard (1778-1835) is born to Samuel Bard (1742-1821) and Mary Bard (1746-1821)
1783 The Revolutionary War ends
1784 Instruction at the College of Physicians and Surgeons begins again
1787 - 1804 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) serves as a Trustee on the Board of Columbia College
January 3, 1791 New York Hospital opens
1790s Samuel Bard (1742-1821) serves as a professor at Columbia College
1792 Susannah Bard (1772- ) marries Judge John Johnston
1796 Francis Upton Johnston is born
1798 William Bard (1778-1835) graduates from Columbia College
1798 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) retires to Hyde Park
1799 John Bard (1716-1799) dies
1802 William Bard (1778-1835) marries Catherine Cruger (1781-1868)
1804 Nathaniel Pendelton participates in the famous Burr-Hamilton duel
1811 St. James Church is consecrated in Hyde Park, on land donated by Samuel Bard
1813 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) is appointed President of the College of Physicians and Surgeons
1817 Enslaved to Samuel Bard, Richard Jenkins (ca. 1783-1857) becomes sexton of St. James Church
1819 John Bard (1819-1899) is born to William Bard (1778-1835) and Catherine Cruger (1781-1868)
1820 Francis Upton Johnston graduates from the College of Physicians and Surgeons
1821 Samuel Bard (1742-1821) and Mary Bard (1746-1821) die within one day of each other and are buried in one grave in the churchyard of St. James.
1822 Francis Upton Johnston marries Mary Williamson
July 4, 1827 enslaved people were emancipated in New York State
1828 Francis Upton Johnston is made attending physician at the New York Hospital
1849 John Bard (1819-1899) marries Margaret Taylor Johnston (1825 -1875)
1852 John and Margaret Johnston Bard purchase Blithewood from John Church Cruger
1857 Chapel of the Holy Innocents was built and dedicated to Willie Bard, as a thank offering for the birth of their son
1860 St. Stephen’s College is founded by the Bards as a training college for young men wishing to pursue theological studies
1868 Willie Bard dies of “malignant fever”; John, Margaret and their daughters Caroline, Emily, and Rosalie, move to Europe
1875 Margaret Taylor Johnston Bard (1825-1875) dies in Rome
1876 John Bard (1819-1899) marries Annie Belcher
1899 John Bard (1819-1899) dies
1934 St. Stephen's College is renamed Bard College
This collection is available for viewing in the Special Collections Reading Room of the Stevenson Library, Bard College.
Peter Bard was the first member of the Bard family in the United States. A Huguenot, Peter Bard was born in France in 1679, and was eventually forced to flee with his father due to religious persecution under Louis XIV. Arriving in the United States in 1706, he settled down in Delaware, near Philadelphia, where he bought a large tract of land in the Burlington township in 1714. It was here that he met Dinah Marmion, who he married in 1709. Peter Bard would continue on to serve on the Colonial Council for New Jersey, become a Commanding Colonel of a foot regiment in 1722, and became a judge for the supreme court of New Jersey. Together, Peter and Dinah had eight children.
The eldest son of Dinah and Peter, John, was born in 1716. John married Susanne Velleau in 1737, and together they moved to Hyde Park, New York. John became a physician, and even served as a family physician to George Washington when he was a General. As a physician, John recommended the purchase of Bedloe's Island (now the Statue of Liberty), as a quarantine site for the isolation of contagious diseases. He also served as the first President of the New York Medical Society. John and Susanne had six children. Their daughter Susanna married Nathaniel Pendelton, who was Alexander Hamilton’s second in the famous duel with Aaron Burr in 1804. Of their children, the most notable of whom was Dr. Samuel Bard.
Samuel was born in Philadelphia in 1742. A sickly child, he had to be removed from school when he was 14 years old. However, this did not stop him from pursuing higher education and he went on to attend King’s college. In 1761, Samuel left to go to England and spend time in London before moving on to study medicine in Edinburgh; but on the second of November, his ship was captured by the French, being thought to be British during the seven years war. Samuel was imprisoned in Bayonne Castle in the small town of St. Jean De Luz, France. Samuel quickly wrote to Benjamin Franklin, who then intervened on his behalf and Samuel was released from the French prison in April of 1762. Later that year, Samuel began college in Edinburgh, studying natural philosophy, anatomy, and chemistry. After graduating as a physician, Samuel returned to New York. In New York, Samuel launched and served as the first president of the College of Physicians and Surgeons, the first medical school in New York City. This medical school was attached to King’s College, later Columbia College. The College pf {physicians and Surgeons was the first medical school to grant the Doctor of Medicine degree in American. Here, he also served as a professor of the theory and practice of medicine, chemistry, natural philosophy, and astronomy. He also served as a Trustee of Columbia College from 1787 to 1804. Along with the college, Samuel founded New York Hospital in 1771.Samuel was not only a leader in American medical education, he also wrote multiple medical books, including one on Midwifery. He also served as George Washington’s personal physician. Samuel was not just a successful physician, he also accumulated large amounts of land in the Hyde Park, New York area, renting large amounts of the land out to tenants and experimenting with sheep farming. He married his cousin, Mary Bard in 1770, and had five children together.
Susanah Bard was the eldest daughter of Samuel and Mary, born in 1772. In 1792, she married John Johnstone. John Johnstone was Judge of the Court of Common Pleas of Dutchess County. Together, Susannah and John had twelve children. Susannah was a caring mother and a devoted christian, often worrying about her children and protecting their souls through the church. Susannah and John often had money problems, and could only afford to send one child to college. They chose their eldest son, Francis Upton Johnston, born in 1796. Francis Upton studied under his grandfather, Samuel Bard, attending the College of Physicians and Surgeons. He graduated college in 1820, and by 1828, he was the attending physician at the New York Hospital. In 1822, he married Mary Williamson, and together they had nine children.
William Bard, the youngest son of Samuel and Mary Bard was born in 1778. He attended Columbia college and graduated in 1798, later becoming a member of the Society of the Cincinnati. In 1802, he married Catharine Cruger and together they had fourteen children. Their son, John, born in 1819, was also a member of the Society of the Cincinnati. John married Maragaret Taylor Johnston in 1849, and together they had 4 children. John founded St. Stephen’s College in 1860, which would become Bard College in 1935. Margaret died in 1875, and John remarried in 1876 to Annie Belcher, with whom he had one child.
This collection documents the life and activities of members of the Bard family over the course of five generations. Members of this family were lawyers, physicians, landlords, homemakers, and were involved in a wide variety of local activities, as well as were familiar with many important people such as George Washington, Benjamin Franklin, and Alexander Hamilton. Correspondence often documents family matters, illness, local news, thoughts on religion and books, and academic and professional concerns. Of note, correspondence includes the courtship between Peter Bard and Dinah Marmion, 1707-1712; several letters from Samuel Bard to his parents during his imprisonment in France, 1761-1762; letters between and among Samuel, Peter, William, John Bard, Susannah Bard and Francis Upton Johnston, 1761-1830 concerning school, travel and family news; and a letter from Nathaniel Pendleton to William Bard describing his role in the Hamilton - Burr duel, 1804.
Materials also document the business and professional affairs of the family. Specifically, there are many land deeds for Bard properties in New Jersey and Dutchess County, New York, as well as indentures and leases of the land. Pertaining to Samuel Bard, there are three manuscript volumes containing the text of lectures on natural philosophy delivered to students at Columbia College, ca. 1793. There is a manuscript volume of family recipes begun by Catherine Cruger Bard in 1803. The founding of St. Stephen's College in 1860 is documented in letters and scrapbooks. There are multiple wills of members of the family and a genealogy chart depicting the family tree.
- Personal Materials, 1638 - 1892
- Correspondence, 1638 - 1892
- Bard Family. Unknown letter, 1638
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Dinah Bard., 1700 - 1749
- Bard, William. Letter to Samuel Bard., 1700 - 1749
- Bard, John. Letter to William Bard., 1700 - 1749
- Bard, John. Letter to Samuel Bard., 1700 - 1749
- Bard, Samuel. Declaration in favor of his son, William Bard., 1700 - 1749
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Dinah Marmion., June 13, 1707
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Samuel Marmion., 1707
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Dinah Marmion., July 16, 1707
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Samuel Marmion., July 28, 1708
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Samuel Marmion, August 9, 1708
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Dinah (Marmion) Bard, October 8, 1709
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Dinah (Marmion) Bard, ca. 1711-1712
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Dinah (Marmion) Bard, October 5, 1712
- Gookin, Charles. Letter to Peter Bard, January 29, 1718
- Parker, John. Letter to Peter Bard, February 19, 1730
- Fauconnier. Letter to Anthony Hecht. Copy., September 29, 1730
- Unknown government official. Letter to Peter Bard, February 26, 1733
- Bard (Marmion), Dinah. Letter to Mary Bard, January 2, 1742
- Bard, Mrs. Dinah (Marmion). Letter to Mrs. Mary (Bard) Campbell, August 19, 1759
- Moore, Mrs. Jochey. Poem to John Bard, 1760
- Valleau, Fauconnier. Bond to Derick Dye, May 19, 1761
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard, July, 1761
- Bard, John. Letter to his son, Samuel Bard, October 29, 1761
- Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard. On being imprisoned., November 28, 1761
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his parents (John and Suzanne (Valleau) Bard), January 23, 1762
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his parents (John and Suzanne (Valleau) Bard). On his deliverance from the French prison., April 27, 1761
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his parents (John and Suzanne (Valleau) Bard)., June 12, 1762
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard., September 25, 1762
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard, November 14, 1762
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard, December 5, 1762
- Bard, John. Letter to Capt. DeWitt. Copy., April 23, 1763
- Bard, Peter. Letter to his brother, Samuel Bard., April 28, 1763
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his cousin, Samuel Bard., June 20, 1763
- Bard, Peter. Letter to his brother, Samuel Bard., August 12, 1763
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his cousin, Dr. Samuel Bard., September 12, 1763
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard., November 10, 1763
- Bard, John. Letter (first draft) to his son, Samuel Bard., December 24, 1763
- Bard, John. Letter to his son, Samuel Bard., December 24, 1763
- Bard, John. Letter to his son, Samuel Bard., January 1, 1764
- Bard, John. Letter to his son, Samuel Bard., January 17, 1764
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his mother, Susanne (Valleau) Bard., February 4, 1764
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard., February 16, 1764
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard., April 9, 1764
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his father, John Bard., April 9, 1764
- Bard, John. Letter to his son, Samuel Bard., April 19, 1764
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to his cousin Samuel Bard., May 18, 1764
- Bard, Peter. Letter to Samuel Bard., November 10, 1764
- Bard, William. Letter to Samuel Bard., 1766
- Bard, William. Letter to Samuel Bard., June 6, 1766
- Bard, John. Letter to his son, Samuel Bard., December 17, 1769
- Bard, John. Letter to Samuel Bard., October 16, 1781
- Bard, William. Letter to Samuel Bard., March 13, 1785
- Bard, William. Letter to his aunt, Mary Martha Campbell., January 24, 1790
- Bard, John. Letter to Rev. and Mrs. Frazer regarding Colin Frazer (Frasier/ Frasier/ Frazier), September 3, 1790
- Bard, Samuel. Letter to Mrs. Henriet Gillespie., March 13, 1791
- Bard, John. Letter to William Bard on preservation., August 3, 1794
- Bard, John. Letter to Mrs. Rebecca Frazer, October 16, 1795
- Thallhimer, Peter. Letter to Samuel Bard concerning the ownership of land in Clifton Park., October 8, 1802
- Pendleton, Nathaniel. Letter to William Bard. Deals with his part as second to Alexander Hamilton in his fatal duel., July 26, 1804
- Pendleton, Nathaniel. Letter to William Bard dealing with political affairs., March 22, 1806
- Washington, Bushrod, 1762-1829 (nephew of George Washington). Letter to William Bard dealing with agricultural problems, August 24, 1806